foreign
do you think of any topics
or
I had one
about different types of pleasant
feelings
um you know there's this these sitters
where the Buddha says
um like why why am I afraid of that type
of pleasant feeling or pleasure that has
nothing to do with
sensuality and nothing to do with
unwholesome States and then in relation
to that
I was thinking about these similes
that are given for
the relief of abandoning the five
hindrances like the relief of
paying off a huge debt or getting out of
prison or
uh getting
to safety after having been through the
desert and so on
and
so like obviously these particular
examples in themselves
like for example the relief of paying
off a desk doesn't in itself
constitute already a pleasure that is no
apart of course yeah
so
so what do those examples have actually
in common with then the pleasure of
sensuality hmm and what and and insofar as they
hmm and what and and insofar as they
actually kind of show the the principle
of non-sensuality within what's in what
way did it do they differ
from yeah so let's let's say like this
yeah so let's let's say like this
how
for example the um
paying off the debt yeah
so what is the debt of sensuality
so imagine if you actually had to pay
off a debt just colloquially speaking
take the principle out of that
and then recognize that principle in
your attitude towards sensuality
because you don't have genres because
the death of centrality hasn't been paid
you're still you're still borrowing
you still keep yourself a debtor
that's the problem so
um what is that that what is that
borrowing that needs to be discerned yeah that
that needs to be discerned yeah that
needs to be seen in regard to centrality
but uh
in in the case of being a just just
needing to pay a debt how does that how
does that feel like how is that
imagine like you go day by day
throughout your days with a debt on your
mind like you have borrowed something
that's not yours
and you know you have to return it or
they'll come for it
well it's a burden uh
so where is then where is then that debt
in regard to centrality I mean somebody
might say I'm living quite restrained
I'm not taking any Central desires yet
there is still no Jannah what means that
still hasn't been paid so where is that
borrowing what are you taking up then
where do you look for that the sex
the sex
the senses yeah yeah how would that
practice how is it practically
manifested taking up of the senses
how are you taking up with the senses
the lighting objects
sure that would be the lighting in
objects would be fueling sensors that
are already taken out rather they will
be fueling taking up with the senses
that's already there but any like you
say taking up with the senses but you
don't take up the eye you don't
consciously think I'll take up the eye
but yeah by passing on to the object
you've taken up the eye but taking up
the eye the ear the nose the tongue the
touches or meeting taking up one thing
or meeting taking up one thing
feeling no so go on look so it sends
itself no you
it's basically the same thing in regard
to which if you're not developed you
will not be free from the body exactly
in that sense and it's the relationship
with the body that's where the debt is
and that's exactly what like in that
suit uh I think the world was talking
about masculinity and femininity but then
masculinity and femininity but then
brought it up and said for as long as a
person is not developed in regards to
their own body they will be a central
desire present so it's you start of
course by withdrawing from the sense
objects and so on but fundamentally that
depth is maintained on the level of your
own relationship with your own body Here
and Now on a day-to-day basis
ownership ownership yes but how is that
like let's make it less abstract how is
that ownership
practically manifested on a day-to-day
basis what is the attitude on a day-to-day
what is the attitude on a day-to-day
basis that you might have in regard to
your own body because of which you're
actually still taking up loans
it's precious it is Pleasant
there is precious that is Pleasant yeah
even if you're not engaging in the
pleasures of it you might still be
taking it as a basis of potential
pleasure and that in and of itself is a
form of delight already
so you're not seeing the Peril of even a
possibility of central pleasure thus the
possibility of central pleasure although
I'm not engaging actually circumstances
are keeping me restrained I'm making the
effort I'm inspired I'm determined
further away at the back of my mind
peripherally over there the actual
future possibility or any possibility or
remote possibility of taking up of
experiencing Central pleasure with the
body is not seen as perilous to that
extent and to that extent you still
you're still a debtor you're still
taking up things
to that extent you have to pay that back
so that's why in order to have the
experience the pleasure of the first
genre you need to have completely
relinquished these these borrowings
these taking UPS these loans and then it
will be a true recognition complete
recognition of I am that free and you
would know that because there will be
nothing at the back of your mind
lingering as a possibility that can
serve for oh payback time now because
you've still been holding on to some
some kind of ambiguous aspect of
valuing uh Pleasures that could be
experienced through the body
so still delighting in them on some
remote level
so like
possibility of somebody doing something
or or or and yeah nothing even specific
just to the fact that well let's say
there you go so you don't have any
specific provocations of Desire you're well
provocations of Desire you're well
restrained but still there's no John
there can only be one reason for that
because you're still not dried up from
sensuality so although you're not engaging you're
so although you're not engaging you're
not kind of making yourself wet again so
to speak with all these like a swamp of
desires you are on the other hand not
dry either
why is that
so even if there are no specific things
or specific uh occasions that might
bring up the desire you're still not dry
up
so what is the what is the basis for
well what is the the bare minimum that
is a sufficient basis for delighting in
centrality what would be the bare
minimum what is one thing you need to do or one
what is one thing you need to do or one
thing you haven't done because of which
you will still Delight even if you're
seeking nothing specifically I'm not
seeing it well exactly not seeing the
danger so that's it you might be well protected
so that's it you might be well protected
you might be well restrained but you
might also not be making the effort to
thoroughly see the danger to the extent
necessary so there is nothing no matter
how far at the back of your mind
uh that maintains lingering of those
values of pleasure on that level where
it would occur it's still nice it's
still not harmful
so it needs to be that that the
knowledge of the harm needs to be seen
through and through and you will know
you saw it when you have the pleasure of
being debt free
so you can't say a fully I'm fully free
from sensuality I thoroughly saw the the
way out I I I'm not taking up anything
but yeah I still don't have Jannah and
that uh pleasure that comes as a result
of being that free
pleasure that comes with being debt free
as in nobody will put themselves into
debt on purpose just to get the relief
of paying off the debts yeah but so it's
beginningless yeah yeah but people
um but people reflect the death of
inflict the pain of sensual desire on
yourself yeah you kind of to get the
relief from us well exactly so that's
the thing so it's it's beginningless
you can't say you were debt free and
then you pick up the debt you just find
yourself in debt because you find
yourself taking up the senses delighting
incense pleasures and you realize oh
yeah people would incur more debt to get
out of debt people do that when you owe
you borrow from somewhere else to pay
this to borrow from somewhere else to
pay this and that's exactly what
centrality is I know scratching the edge
makes things worse
but that immediate level it provides a
relief that I have
that I don't have any I have none of so
any relief so relief from this debt is
better although I have borrowed from another
although I have borrowed from another
person so I'm technically still in debt
but at least I believe this so it's just
moving it's a sort of uh having an
active that feels like it's better than
just recognize that you're always
indebted it's like covering up your eyes
like oh yeah but no see I pay this
person off I don't own him I got the
pleasure from being that free
because I borrowed it from over here but
I won't look there for now when that
becomes unavoidable I'll borrow from
somewhere else
to pay that off just to deal with it
when it comes when the pressure comes
too much so fundamentally you fully
remain in that domain of debt
so it's the danger it's not seeing the
danger sufficiently thoroughly
frequently enough
the Delight the light would still linger
the possibilities would still be there
and you won't be that free although as I
said you might live your life perfectly
restrained and withdrawn from sensuality
that has not been fully kind of
uprooted pushed out so to speak uh the
mind can still remain attracted to it so
you you might have dried your sticks
um you might have taken the sticks out
of the water but they're still not
thoroughly dried on on the inside
so you still can't light the fire
and that's it it's just drying up things
through contemplating the danger of the
right things of the right experiences of
the right
of the right order
but then with that kind of
imply that you still cultivate some
Delight on the mental level at least
would what imply that
being almost sufficiently dry but still not
almost sufficiently dry but still not
experiencing the pleasure of yeah yeah
because you still haven't and that's
what I mean you would be cultivating
that Delight simply by not seeing the
danger nothing else required
nothing else required
you don't need to be actively thinking
about sensuality to still have
to still have some degree of of debt
so delizing in uh to any degree in
uh objects of sensuality already has to
imply the lighting in the body oh yeah
yeah yeah the body is has to have been
taken up and and that's not it's on that
level like you can kind of it's obvious
enough that oh yeah like this is
delightful this object but you don't
even you won't see that it won't even
see on that negative peripheral level
yeah yeah that's where the sensory
strain needs to come first that's what
sensory sense restraint withdrawal or um
overcoming through not acting towards
overcoming concern towards the world
through basically not acting and
engaging with the world engaging with
information engaging with distraction
that sort of as I said before brings you
back and then reveals that body that you
are taking up
so then you can see it as a phenomenon
there uh as a basis of potential pleasure that
uh as a basis of potential pleasure that
then you choose to oh yeah I'll take
this so that I engage with these objects
that becomes more apparent but for as
long as you're still distracted or
immersed in the objects
you you you're looking past it you're
not seeing it
[Music] so step intake restraining stepping back
so step intake restraining stepping back
yeah so it's like people say I'll step
back it's not a matter of intention you
can't choose to step back well you can
but that's not the type of stepping back
we're talking about
you can have a sense of stepping back
sure but the stepping back here is
created by actually actively refusing to
go back physically into domain of
sensuality through action through body
speech and so on so basically keeping
the precept guarding of the sense doors
will push you back
so that then you see the basis that
you've been taking up at face value with
your sense of self like to be yours to
be justifiably used for gaining pleasure
and enjoyment in this world and that is
this body
so if you then contemplate the the
danger of taking that up oh you won't
have to worry about enticing sense
objects that's way too down the line
so then you could kind of contemplate
the well the disgusting nature of the body
well the disgusting nature of the body
on that level yeah only on the basis of
thyroid restraint and then Discerning
this body that endures while I'm
restrained you have to see it it's not
just because if people otherwise just
take up contemplation of the disgusting
body but while their mind is still on
the level of sense objects that's not
the body they're contemplating they're
just gonna like uh it's it's they're
contemplating it through perverted order
still so it doesn't apply to what it
should contemplate the body the
disgusting body while not taking it up
having not taken it up oh have you not
taking it up two cents restraint and
guarding of the sense doors not for a
night or two but for much longer it
takes time to dry up it takes time for
that aggregate to Virtue to sort of gain
weight so to speak and and and and be
palpable there
recognize well if you're honest what it is doing
well if you're honest what it is doing
it right or not whether the
contemplation of the disgusting nature
yeah is kind of on the level of objects
and it's kind of like yeah secondary or
whether it's actually but the thing is
even the honest reminding the
possibility of even the honesty comes up
with withdrawal yeah so if people know
the Drone they can think they're honest
then might not necessarily be honest
yeah so that's why first things first
please sits and guarding the sends those
uh not distracting yourself and
overcoming concern towards the the world
Joys and concerns not dealing with the
world not being engaged with it not
being actively emotionally
tied to it the the pleasure of
withdrawal would be determined by what
you will be drawn from but the Peril but
by The Weight by the pain that used to
have on account of it
right because see that's always it's
always at the back of your mind
every time you borrow every time you
take up that to that extent
um the uncertainty
you become liable to uncertainty to loss
to more pressure and you know that every
time the sickness the sickness every
time so to the extent that you're taking
things up to from from from here so I'm
taking up basically I'm relying to sense
Pleasures to to avoid the pressure of
the body the the partigo of the senses
the the pain of sense restraint
I know each time to the extent I take to
that extent I remain connected to
uncertainty to pain to loss to liability
to dukkha of any kind
but if you don't take it up at any on
any level and relinquish that which
pressures you I the body that natural
patiga we spoke about before
then it was oh this is truly blameless
I'm I've relinquished the pain I've
relinquished that without incurring more
debt and you would feel that at the back of
and you would feel that at the back of
your mind that that well that
release and that's a release that doesn't depend
and that's a release that doesn't depend
on doing anything exactly exacting your
circumstances in any level and that's
exactly why you did not incur more debt
but by doing it yeah and that's that's
what I recognize wait why am I afraid of
this pleasure that is blameless that
does not have more debt as it's as its
base oh let me then pursue it so he pursued
oh let me then pursue it so he pursued
the pleasure of volsa guys we spoke
before the pleasure of relinquishing but
relinquishing needs to be done on the
level of
that which you're not relinquishing
which is your body you can't just go
around I don't well you can I suppose it
would be a useful practice in the
beginning but that's not what we're
talking about we're talking about
relinquishing that necessary basis for
your uh state of debt for your state of
peril for the liability of dukkha and that is
for the liability of dukkha and that is
your relationship with your own body
that's what you're taking up that patiga
that discomfort of of having this lump
of Flesh this form
you need to delinquish having not being
incurring having not sort of constantly
trying to cover it up by incurring more
depth of sensuality and Central
pleasures but then yes relinquishing it would
but then yes relinquishing it would
equal the release
because you're not doing anything you're
just giving up that you're just not
taking what you used to take what you're
usually taking up
so it's not like you're replacing it
with something else you're giving it up
and that is the kind of you could say
that's a prerequisite for Jana that that
was okay that giving up relinquishment
contemplating relinquishment the mind
will enter the first John
obviously relinquishment as I said of
the right things on the right level
so what is that body then
say somebody is properly restrained
withdrawn overcoming concern Joys towards the
overcoming concern Joys towards the
world not distracting themselves
how would you describe from the internal
point of view
you and the relationship with his body
what is it how is it how is it found
how do you not take it up how do you
relinquish it
look what I'm saying is sense restraint
withdrawal will kind of put you in a
position to discern this body but she
has to have to discern it
for as long as
a monk is not developed in regard to his
own body
he's not free from centrality so how is
one developed in regard to his own body
I'll do how do you develop that
um like Alex was saying it's about being
discussed in regards to that we're
seeing it on the right level seeing the
seeing the discuss practicing the super
on the right level yeah
so
um
[Music]
very obvious yeah that's the thing
exactly so when you are withdrawn from
centrality when you are when you are not
approaching your own body through the
perverted order of your own senses first
or if you sense objects first
you would even yeah just contemplating
skin head ears teeth
head ears teeth
literally they're just things like these
stones and soil and wood and grass
just in a particular pile but same you
know calcium and tissue and water and
elements that's it
that's it pile of stone pile of wood
pile of Flesh
so
from that
peripheral point of view as I said the
one that you have been withdrawn from
and you see your body there now as one
of these things
that's like yeah that's you don't need
to do more
to then discern the unknown ability of
it and so on you just need to protect it
maintain it
and then also as I said before
contemplate the danger of
losing the sight of the body on that
level which basically equals losing
which basically equals losing
mindfulness
because most people practice mindfulness
through the perverted order of sense
objects first and then I I feel my
Sensations and watch this as objects of
my experience
now you got to withdraw yourself from
all of that stop engaging with it to
discern this body that's already here
necessary basis for any direction that
I'm activating myself and doing it and
then start seeing that body that endures
there whether they think about it or not
as a that's completely unable given
outside of like I did not create it
shape it form it and I can certainly not
step outside of it yet my whole
perception feeling my whole entire my
whole experience my whole being depends
on the existence of it because if these
elements they compose this body will
just disintegrate that's it
the Aggregates could not Remain the rest
of the aggraves could not remain
standing so if those contemplations see anybody
so if those contemplations see anybody
can think these things but if they're
not resulting
in release
in in kind of furthering of the release
in furthering of of kind of uh
losing the desire towards sense objects
then you're not contemplating on the
right level
that means you're not you still haven't
taken your sticks even out of the water
you're not you're not restrained you
might be somewhat restrained or you
might be more restrained than you used
to be but that's still not sufficient
yes if you are restrained then it would
actually kind of be hard not to do it
that's what I mean yeah that's what I
mean like the Buddha would instruct
people with the gradual training they
would have to result
in drying up withdrawal Chana Right View
Jana and so on you would have to so if
it's not oh it's because you haven't
completed this first so you're trying to
to build the second and the third floor
and so on
uh while the the basis is still like
lacking not complete
yes the danger of like you like you just
said the danger of losing perspective
that kind of perspective and that sense
of that danger that's the only thing you
should be afraid of by the way
you have to feed anything else
at all
and he's like actually that's a good
deal instead of feeding everything and
nothing I'll just fear this one thing losing the
I'll just fear this one thing losing the
mindfulness of the body on the right
level which you're completely
responsible which is entirely always
like in my control whether I do it or
not just because I'm intentionally doing
it or not
um and if that's all you protect well
that's all you need to protect then
everything else that happens and so on
it's like it won't be a fault it won't
be it won't be a blameworthy thing
because it's not done through the
Gateway of Desire Gateway of Desire
being taking up the body ignorantly this
through a distracted manner
as a basis for pleasure yeah
and something someone said in regards to
that which inspires well can inspired a lot
which inspires well can inspired a lot
of sense of urgencies
when you lose that perspective
in whatever way there is no guarantee
that you are getting back to it because
if you just distract yourself
well enough
you might yeah well you might run out of
time we run out of time in the meantime
you might be able to get back if you
were to have time but you might not have
time you don't know as I said
contemplating the unknown ability of the
body so it's not like so what do I do
next what do I do next no this is what
you do you just don't fall from this
that's it so there's no let go and then
the next step and then the next step you
know just protect and purify this step
says or he practices mindfulness to the
body whichever way you want to translate it
whichever way you want to translate it
to the extent necessary for the final
knowledge so he purifies the relationship between
so he purifies the relationship between
him and his own body relinquishes it to
the extent necessary
for final knowledge that's it
for the final knowledge complete Freedom
yeah relinquishing with all ownership of any
relinquishing with all ownership of any
base for suffering done
and they say oh if he doesn't get the
orange this life well then at least be a
non-runner return
there are these other cities
keep that
just keep that that your work's done
and the results of other hand chip and
so on will have to follow if not well it
leaves sanagame will have to follow
if that relationship is uprooted and
relinquished on the right level and
protected to sense restraint and gradual training
so that how long that has to be done
that's not up to you
that's up to how much Killers how much
obstructions you have had through the
countless times of you know engaging
with samsara so for some people it would
be as would have said
seven years of having to protect that
some people would be seven months some
people would be half a night but as I
said I'll always say I think it's we can
it's a safe bet that today two and a
half thousand years after the Buddha
we're probably on that longer end of
that uh Spectrum
so 17 years
but again it's Pleasant to buy in here
right now so it's not 17 years of
torture maybe 17 years of reminding
yourself how you're debt free because
you relinquish the basis of pleasure and
any further borrowing so it's a win-win
you lose nothing really exactly things
you lose absolutely nothing exactly yeah
cannot yeah exactly it